<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A speech delivered in Parliament, by a worthy member thereof, and a most faithfull vvell-wisher to the Church and Common-weale; concerning the grievances of the kingdome. By I.P. Esquire.</title>
            <author>Pym, John, 1584-1643.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91395</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P4284</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E198_35</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14550</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859688</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859688</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111783</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91395)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111783)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 35:E198[35])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A speech delivered in Parliament, by a worthy member thereof, and a most faithfull vvell-wisher to the Church and Common-weale; concerning the grievances of the kingdome. By I.P. Esquire.</title>
                  <author>Pym, John, 1584-1643.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. L.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A variant of the edition with "printed for R. Lownes" in imprint.</note>
                  <note>Title page has printers' device (McK. 263-267).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111783:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:111783:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SPEECH DELIVERED IN PARLIAMENT, BY A worthy MEMBER thereof, AND A moſt faithfull VVell-wiſher to the CHURCH and COMMON-WEALE; Concerning the grievances of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>By <hi>I. P.</hi> Eſquire.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:111783:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111783:2"/>
            <head>A SPEECH DELIVERED In PARLIAMENT, BY A worthy Member therof, and a moſt faithfull well-wiſher to the CHURCH and COMMON-WEALE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ever Parliament had greater buſineſſes to diſpatch, nor more difficulties to <note place="margin">The precedent conſideration of grievances will further the ſupply</note> encounter; therefore wee have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to take all advantages of order and addreſſe, and hereby we ſhall not only doe our owne worke, but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſe and inable our ſelves for the better ſatisfaction
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111783:3"/>
of his Majeſties deſire of ſupply. The grievances being removed, our affections will carry us with ſpeede and cheerefulneſſe, to give his Majeſtie that which may bee ſufficient both for his honour and ſupport. Thoſe that in firſt place ſhall endeavour to redreſſe the grievances, will be found not to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but to bee the beſt furtherers of his Majeſties ſervice: hee that takes away weights, doth as much advantage motion, as he that addeth wings.</p>
            <p>Divers pieces of this maine worke have beene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready <note place="margin">Great workes are firſt to bee conſidered in the modell.</note> propounded, his endeavour ſhould be to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the Houſe a modell of the whole. In the Creation God made the world according to that <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea</hi> or forme, which was eternally preexiſtent in the divine minde, <hi>Moſes</hi> was commanded to frame the Tabernacle after the patterne ſhewed him in the Mount. Thoſe actions are ſeldome well perfected in the execution, which are not firſt well moulded in the deſigne, and propoſition.</p>
            <p>He ſaid, he would labour to contract thoſe mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold <note place="margin">A double me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod <hi>compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> of grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and cures.</note> affaires both of the Church and State, which did ſo earneſtly require the wiſedome and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this Houſe, into a double method of grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and cures: and becauſe there wanted not ſome who pretended, that theſe things wherwith the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth is now grieved, are much for the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the King, and that the redreſſe of them will be to his Majeſties great diſadvantage and loſſe (hee <note place="margin">Publike grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious to the King.</note> ſaid) he doubted not but to make it appeare, that is diſcovering the preſent great diſtempers and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and procuring remedie for them, we ſhould bee no leſſe ſerviceable to his Majeſtie, who hath ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned us to this great Councell, than uſefull to thoſe whom we doe here repreſent: for the better effecting
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111783:3"/>
whereof, he propounded three maine branches of his <note place="margin">The firſt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall diviſion.</note> diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>In the firſt (he ſaid) he would offer them the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> heads of ſome principall grievances, under which the Kingdome groaned.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond, he undertook to prove, that the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> from whence thoſe grievances iſſued, were as hurtfull to the King as to the people.</p>
            <p>In the third, he would adviſe ſuch a way of heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and removing thoſe grievances, as might bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually effectuall to maintaine the honour and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the King, and to procure the proſperitie and contentment of the people.</p>
            <p>In the handling whereof he promiſed to uſe ſuch <note place="margin">Sharpe matters to be mitiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion.</note> expreſſions as might mitigate the ſharpneſſe and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe of thoſe things whereof hee was to ſpeake, ſo farre as his dutie and faithfulneſſe would allow. It is a great Prerogative to the King, and a great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour <note place="margin">The King can do no wrong.</note> attributed to him, in a Maxime of our Law, that he can doe no wrong, he is the fountaine of Iuſtice: and if there be any injuſtice in the execution of his Commands, the Law caſts it upon the Miniſters, and frees the King. Activitie, life, and vigour, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed into the ſublunary creatures, by the influence of Heaven: but the malignitie and diſtemper, the cauſe of ſo many Fpidemicall diſeaſes, doe proceed from the noyſome vapours of the earth, or ſome ill affected qualities of the aire, without any infection or alteration of thoſe pure, celeſtiall and incorruptible bodies. In the like manner (he ſaid) the authoritie, the power and countenance of Princes may concur in the actions of evill men, without partaking in the injuſtice and obliquitie of them. Theſe matters whereof we complaine, have beene preſented to his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111783:4"/>
Majeſtie, either under the pretence of Royall prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives, <note place="margin">Hurtfull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects preſented to the King under plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble notions.</note> which he is bound to maintaine, or of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like good, which is the moſt honourable object of Regall wiſedome. But the covetous and ambitious deſignes of others, have interpoſed betwixt his Royall intentions, and the happineſſe of his people, making thoſe things pernicious and hurtfull, which his Majeſtie apprehended as juſt, and profitable.</p>
            <p>He ſaid, the things which he was to propound, <note place="margin">A promiſe of moderation.</note> were of a various nature, many of them ſuch as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired a very tender and exquiſite conſideration, In handling of which, as he would be bold to uſe the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the place and relation wherein he ſtood, ſo he would be carefull to expreſſe that Modeſtie and humilitie, which might be expected by thoſe, of whoſe actions he was to ſpeake. And if his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <note place="margin">Submiſſion to reformation.</note> or his tongue ſhould ſlip into any particular miſtake, he would not thinke it ſo great a ſhame, to faile by his owne weakeneſſe, as hee ſhould eſteeme it an honour and advantage, to be corrected by the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of that Houſe, to which he ſubmitted himſelf, with this proteſtation, that he deſired no reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo much as to reforme himſelfe.</p>
            <p>The greateſt libertie of the Kingdome, is Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <note place="margin">Religion.</note> thereby we are freed from ſpirituall evils: and no impoſitions are ſo grievous, as thoſe that are laid upon the ſoule. The next great libertie is Iuſtice, <note place="margin">Iuſtice.</note> whereby we are preſerved from injuries in our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; and eſtates, from this is derived into the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, peace, and order, and ſafetie, and when this is interrupted, confuſion and danger are ready to overwhelme all: The third great libertie conſiſts <note place="margin">Priviledge of Parliament.</note> in the power and priviledge of Parliaments, this is the fountaine of law, the great Councell of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111783:4"/>
Kingdome, the higheſt Court: this is inabled by the Legiſlative and Conſiliarie power, to prevent evils to come; by the Judiciarie power, to ſuppreſſe and remove evils preſent. If you conſider theſe three great liberties in the order of dignitie, this laſt is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to the other two, as Meanes are inferiour to <note place="margin">The order propounded in handling theſe 3 great li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties.</note> the end; but if you conſider them in the order of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, and uſe, this may juſtly claime the firſt place, in our care, becauſe the end cannot be obtained with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the meanes: if we doe not preſerve this, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not long hope to enjoy either of the other. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (hee ſaid) being to ſpeake of thoſe grievances which lie upon the Kingdome, hee would obſerve this order.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Firſt to mention thoſe, which were againſt the priviledge of Parliaments.</item>
               <item>2. Thoſe which were prejudiciall to the Religion eſtabliſhed in the Kingdome.</item>
               <item>3. Thoſe which did interrupt the juſtice of the Realme, in the libertie of our perſons, and propriety of our eſtates.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The priviledges of Parliament were not given <note place="margin">The neceſſitie and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the priviledge of Parliament.</note> for the ornament or advantage of thoſe, who are the members of Parliament, they have a reall uſe and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacie, towards that which is the end of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: we are free from ſuits, that we may the more intirely addict our ſelves, to the publike ſervices: we have therefore libertie of ſpeech, that our Counſels may not be corrupted with feare, or our judgements perverted with ſelfe reſpects; thoſe three great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties and functions of Parliament, the Legiſlative, Iudiciarie, and Conſiliarie power, can not bee well exerciſed without ſuch priviledges as theſe. The wiſedome of our Lawes, the faithfullneſſe of our
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111783:5"/>
Counſels, the righteouſneſſe of our Iudgements can hardly be kept pure and untainted, if they proceed from diſtracted and reſtrained mindes.</p>
            <p>It is a good Rule of the Morall Philoſopher, <hi>Et non laedas mentem gubernatricem omnium actionum:</hi> Theſe powers of Parliament are to the bodie poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike as the rationall faculties of the ſoule, to a man. That which keepes all the parts of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth in frame, and temper, ought to be moſt care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully preſerved in that freedome, vigour, and activi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which belongs to it ſelf. Our predeceſſors in this houſe, have ever been moſt carefull in the firſt place, to ſettle and ſecure their priviledges: and (he ſaid) he hoped that we having had greater breaches made upon us than heretofore, would be no leſſe tender of them, and forward in ſeeking reparation for that which is paſt, and prevention of the like for the time to come.</p>
            <p>Then hee propounded divers particular points <note place="margin">Particular brea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches of Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</note> wherein the Priviledge of Parliament had beene broken.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in reſtraining the members of the Houſe <note place="margin">1 Reſtraint of ſpeech.</note> from ſpeaking.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in forbidding the Speaker to put any <note place="margin">2 Interdict of queſtions.</note> Queſtion.</p>
            <p>Theſe two were practiſed the laſt day of the laſt Parliament (and, as was alledged, by his Majeſties command) and both of them trench upon the very life and being of Parliaments, for if ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining power as this ſhould take root, and bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, it will be impoſſible for us to bring any reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to perfection in ſuch matters as ſhall diſpleaſe thoſe about the King.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, by impriſoning divers Members of <note place="margin">Impriſonment of Members.</note>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:111783:5"/>
the Houſe for matters done in Parliament.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, by indictments, informations, and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <note place="margin">Iudiciall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings.</note> inordinarie and inferiour Courts, for ſpeeches and proceedings in Parliaments.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, the diſgracefull order of the Kings <note place="margin">Order to bee bound to the good behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</note> Bench, whereby ſome members of this Houſe were injoyned to put in ſecuritie of the good beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and for refuſall thereof, they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in priſon, divers yeares, without any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular allegation againſt them: one of them was freed by death, others not diſmiſſed till his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie had declared his intention, to ſummon this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. And this he noted, not only as a breach of priviledge, but as a violation of the common juſtice of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, by the ſudden and abrupt diſſolution of <note place="margin">Abrupt diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</note> Parliaments, contrary to the law and cuſtome. It hath beene often declared in Parliaments, that the Parliament ſhould not be diſſolved, till the petitions be anſwered. This (he ſaid) was a great grievance becauſe it doth prevent the redreſſe of other grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances.</p>
            <p>It were a hard Caſe, that a private man ſhould bee put to death without being heard: As this repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative body of the Commons, receives a being by the ſummons, ſo it receives a Civill death by the diſſolution. Is it not a much more heaviedoome, by which wee loſe our being, and have this civill death inflicted on us, in diſpleaſure, and not to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed time and libertie to anſwer for our ſelves? that we ſhould not only die, but have this marke of infamy laid upon us, to bee made <hi>Inteſtabiles,</hi> diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to make our Wills, to diſpoſe of our buſineſſe, as this Houſe hath alwayes uſed to doe, before Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journments
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111783:6"/>
or diſſolutions? yet this, hath often beene our caſe; we have not beene permitted to powre out our laſt ſighes and groanes, into the boſome of our deare Soveraigne; the words of dying men are full of piercing affections: if we might be heard to ſpeake, no doubt wee ſhould ſo fully expreſſe our love, and faithfulneſſe to our Prince, as might take off the falſe ſuggeſtions and aſperſions of others: at leaſt we ſhould in our humble ſupplications, recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend ſome ſuch things to him in the name of his people, as would make for his owne honour, and the publike good of his Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Thus hee concluded the firſt ſort of grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <note place="margin">Grievances concerning re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</note> being ſuch as were againſt the priviledge of Parliament, and paſſed on to the next, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Religion: all which hee conveyed under theſe foure heads.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The firſt, was the great incouragement given <note place="margin">Incourageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of poperie.</note> to poperie, of which he produced theſe particular e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences.</p>
            <p n="1">1 A ſuſpenſion of all Lawes againſt Papiſts, <note place="margin">Suſpenſion of Lawes.</note> whereby they enjoy a free, and almoſt publike ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of that Religion, and thoſe good Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes which were made for reſtraint of Idolatrie, and ſuperſtition, are now a ground of ſecuritie to them, in the practice of both, being uſed to no other end, but to get money into the Kings purſe: which as it is clearely againſt the intentions of the Law, ſo it is full of miſchiefe to the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>By this meanes a dangerous partie is cheriſhed, and increaſed, who are ready to cloſe with any op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie of diſturbing the peace and ſafetie of the State. Yet (hee ſaid) hee did not deſire any new
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111783:6"/>
Lawes againſt poperie, or any rigorous courſes in the execution of thoſe alreadie in force; hee was farre from ſeeking the ruine of their perſons or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, onely hee wiſht they might bee kept in ſuch a condition, as ſhould reſtraine them from doing hurt.</p>
            <p>It may bee objected, there are moderate and <note place="margin">There can bee no ſecuritie from papiſts.</note> diſcreet men amongſt them, men of eſtates, ſuch as have an intereſt in the peace and proſperitie of the Kingdome, as well as wee. Theſe (hee ſaid) were not to bee conſidered according to their owne diſpoſition, but according to the nature of the <note place="margin">but In their diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie.</note> body, whereof they are parties. The Planets have ſeverall and particular motions of their owne, yet they are all rapt and tranſported into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie courſe, by the ſuperiour Orbe which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends them all. The principles of Poperie are ſuch, as are incompatible with any other Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: there may bee a ſuſpenſion of violence, for ſome by reſpects, but the ultimate end, even of that moderation, is, that they may with more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage extirpate that which is oppoſite to them. Lawes will nto reſtraine them, Oathes will not, the Pope can diſpence with both theſe, and where there is occaſion, his command will act them, to the diſturbance of the Realme, againſt their owne private diſpoſition, yea, againſt their owne reaſon and judgement to obey him, to whome they have (eſpecially the Ieſuiticall partie) ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely and intirely obliged themſelves, not onely in ſpirituall matters, but in temporall, as they are in order <hi>ad Spiritualia, Henry</hi> the third, and <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth of <hi>France,</hi> were no Proteſtants themſelves, yet were murthered, becauſe they
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111783:7"/>
tolerated the proteſtants, by which and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preſidents it appeares, that the King, that the Kingdome can have no ſecuritie but in their weaknes and diſabilitie to doe hurt.</p>
            <p n="2">2 A ſecond incouragement is, their admiſſion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">Admiſſion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to places of power.</note> places of power and truſt in the Common wealth, whereby they get many dependants and adherents, not only of their owne, but even of ſuch as make profeſſion to be proteſtants.</p>
            <p n="3">3 A third, their freedome of reſorting to <hi>London,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Free reſort to London and the Court.</note> and the Court, whereby they have opportunitie, not only of Communicating their Counſels, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes one to another, but of diving into his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Counſels, by the frequent acceſſe of thoſe who are active men amongſt them, to the tables and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of great men, and under ſubtile pretences and diſguiſes, they want not meanes of cheriſhing their owne projects, and of indeavouring to mould and biaſſe the publike affaires to the great advantage of that partie.</p>
            <p n="4">4 A fourth, that as they have a congregation of Cardinals at <hi>Rome,</hi> to conſider of the apteſt wayes and meanes of eſtabliſhing the Popes authoritie and Religion in <hi>England,</hi> ſo they have a Nuncio here, to act and diſpoſe that partie to the execution of thoſe counſels, and by the aſſiſtance of ſuch cunning and Ieſuiticall ſpirits as ſwarme in this town, to order and mannage all actions, and events, to the furtherance of that maine end.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſecond grievance in Religion, was from <note place="margin">Innovations in matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</note> thoſe manifold innovations lately introduced into ſeverall parts of the Kingdome, all inclining to pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and diſpoſing and fitting men to entertaine it: the particulars are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:111783:7"/>
1 Divers of the chiefeſt points of Religion in <note place="margin">Maintainance of popiſh te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets.</note> difference betwixt us and the papiſts have beene publikely defended in licenſed Bookes, in Sermons, in Vniverſitie acts and diſputations.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Divers popiſh Ceremonies have beene not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly practiſed, <note place="margin">Practice of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</note> but countenanced, yea little leſſe than injoyned, as Altars, Images, Crucifixes, bowings, and other geſtures and obſervances, which put upon our Churches a ſhape and face of poperie. Hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared this to the drie bones in <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> firſt they came together, then the ſinewes and the fleſh came upon them, after this the skin covered them, and then breath and life was put into them: ſo (he ſaid) after theſe men had moulded us into an outward forme and viſage of poperie, they would more bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endeavour to breath into us the ſpirit and life of poperie.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The third grievance, was the countenancing <note place="margin">Preferment of men popiſhly inclined.</note> and preferring thoſe men, who were moſt forward in ſetting up ſuch Innovations, the particulars were ſo well knowne, that they needed not to be named.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The fourth was, the diſcouragement of thoſe <note place="margin">Diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of true profeſſors.</note> who were knowne to bee moſt conſcionable, and faithfull profeſſors of the truth: ſome of the wayes of effecting this, he obſerved to be theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The courſes taken to inforce and inlarge thoſe <note place="margin">Inlargement of the differences among our ſelves.</note> unhappy differences, for matters of ſmall moment, which have beene amongſt our ſelves, and to raiſe up new occaſions of further diviſion, whereby ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have beene induced to forſake the land, not ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the end of thoſe voluntarie and humane Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in things appertaining to Gods worſhip: whereas thoſe who are indeed lovers of Religion, and of the Churches of God, would ſeeke to make up thoſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111783:8"/>
breaches, and to unite us more entirely againſt the common enemie.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The over rigid proſecution of thoſe who are <note place="margin">Over-rigid proſecution of the ſcrupulous for things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different.</note> ſcrupulous in uſing ſome things enjoyned, which are held by thoſe who enjoyn them, to be in themſelvs indifferent. It hath beene ever the derſie of this Houſe, expreſt in many Parliaments in Queene <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeths</hi> time and ſince, that ſuch might bee tenderly uſed. It was one of our petitions delivered at <hi>Oxford</hi> to his Majeſtie that now is: but what little modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it hath produced, is not unknowne to us all, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other vice almoſt may be better indured in a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter than Inconformitie.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The unjuſt puniſhments, and vexations of ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry <note place="margin">Vnjuſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not by law.</note> perſons for matters required, without any war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of Law: as</p>
            <p>For not reading the booke concerning recreation <note place="margin">Reading the booke.</note> on the Lords day.</p>
            <p>For not removing the Communion Table to bee <note place="margin">The Table ſet Altarwiſe.</note> ſet Altarwiſe at the Eaſt end of the Chancell.</p>
            <p>For not comming up to the Railes to receive the <note place="margin">Comming to the Railes.</note> Sacrament.</p>
            <p>For preaching the Lords day in the afternoone.</p>
            <p>For catechiſing in any other words and manner <note place="margin">Preaching up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lords day. Varying from the chatechiſm</note> than in the preciſe words of the ſhort chatechiſme in the Common prayer booke.</p>
            <p>The fifth and laſt grievance concerning Religion, <note place="margin">Abuſe of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction.</note> was the incroachment and abuſe of Eccleſiaſticall ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction: the particulars mentioned are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Fining and impriſoning in caſes not allowed <note place="margin">In fining and impriſoning.</note> by law.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Their challenging their juriſdiction to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate <note place="margin">Claiming ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction to be <hi>Jure Divino.</hi>
               </note> to their order, which they alledge to be <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Divino.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:111783:8"/>
3 The contriving and publiſhing of new articles, <note place="margin">Articles of the viſitations.</note> upon which they inforce the Churchwardens to take oathes, and to make inquiries and preſentments, as if ſuch articles had the force of Canons: and this, he ſaid, was an effect of great preſumption and bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, not onely in the Biſhops, but in their Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons, Officials, and Chancellours, taking upon themſelves a kinde of Synodall authoritie: and the Injunctions of this kinde, might well partake in name with that part of the common law, which is called the Extravagants.</p>
            <p>Having diſpatcht theſe ſeverall points, hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded <note place="margin">Grievances concerning the libertie of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates.</note> to the third kinde of grievances, being ſuch as are againſt the common juſtice of the Realm, in the libertie of our perſons, and proprietie of our eſtates, of which (he ſaid) he had many to propound: In doing whereof, hee would rather obſerve the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of time, wherin they were acted, than of conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence: but when hee ſhould come to the cure, hee ſhould then perſwade the Houſe to begin with thoſe, who were of moſt importance, as being now in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, and very much preſſing and exhauſting the Common wealth.</p>
            <p>He began with the Tonnage and Poundage, and <note place="margin">Tonnage and Poundage im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions.</note> other impoſitions not warranted by law: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe theſe burdens had long lyen upon us, and the principles which produced them, are the ſame from whence divers others are derived, hee thought it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to premiſe a ſhort narrative, and relation of the grounds and proceedings of the power of impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <note place="margin">Not to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken but by conſent in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</note> herein practiſed. It was (hee ſaid) a fundamental truth eſſential to the conſtitution and government of this Kingdom, an hereditarie liberty and priviledge of al the free born ſubjects of the land, that no tax, tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, or
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111783:9"/>
other charge might be laid upon us, without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <note place="margin">Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour.</note> conſent in Parliament, this was acknowledged by the Conquerour, ratified in that contract which he made with this Nation, upon his admittance to the Kingdome, declared and confirmed in the lawes which he publiſhed.</p>
            <p>This hath never beene denyed to any of our Kings, <note place="margin">Sometimes broken by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Kings, but never denyed.</note> though broken and interrupted by ſome of them, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially by King <hi>Iohn,</hi> and <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. then againe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by <hi>Mag. Chart.</hi> and other ſucceeding lawes: yet not ſo well ſetled, but that it was ſometime at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted by the two ſucceeding <hi>Edwards,</hi> in whoſe times <note place="margin">Thoſe brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches repaired by ſucceeding Parliaments.</note> the ſubjects were very ſenſible of all the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches made upon the common libertie, and by the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie of frequent Parliaments, purſued them with freſh complaints, and for the moſt part, found redreſſe, and procured the right of the ſubject to bee fortified by new Statutes.</p>
            <p>He obſerved, that thoſe Kings, even in the Acts <note place="margin">Some mixture of evidence for the ſubject in theſe very breaches.</note> whereby they did breake the law, did really affirme the ſubjects libertie, and diſclaim that right of impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, which is now challenged, for they did uſually procure the Merchants conſent, to ſuch taxes as were laid, thereby to put a colour of juſtice upon their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding,, and ordinarily they were limited to a ſhort time, and then propounded to the ratification of the Parliament, where they were cancell'd or confirmed, as the neceſſity and ſtate of the Kingdom did require.</p>
            <p>But for the moſt part, ſuch charges upon merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, <note place="margin">The grant by parliament moſt uſuall.</note> were taken by authoritie of Parliament, and granted for ſome ſhort time, in a greater or leſſer pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, as was requiſite for ſupply of the publike oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, ſix or twelve in the pound, for one, two, or three yeares, as they ſaw cauſe, to bee imployed for
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111783:9"/>
the defence of the Sea, and it was acknowledged ſo clearely to be in the power of Parliament, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they <note place="margin">At firſt variouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly limited, in reſpect of time and perſons. Afterwards, Confirmed to the King for life.</note> have ſometimes beene granted to Noble men, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to Merchants to bee diſpoſed for that uſe. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward they were granted to the King for life, and ſo continued for divers deſcents, yet ſtill as a gift and grant of the Commons.</p>
            <p>Betwixt the time of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, and Queene <note place="margin">No contrary practice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Edw. 3 and Q. Mary.</note> 
               <hi>Maay,</hi> never Prince (that he could remember) offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to demand any impoſition, but by grant in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament: Queene <hi>Mary</hi> laid a charge upon cloth, by the equitie of the Statute of Tunnage and Poundage, becauſe the rate ſet upon wooll was much more than upon cloth: and there being little wooll carried out <note place="margin">Pretended e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie for the Cuſtome upon cloth.</note> of the Kingdom unwrought, the Q. thought ſhe had reaſon, to lay ſomewhat more, yet not f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll ſo much, as brought them to an equalitie, but that ſtill there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued a leſſe charge upon wooll wrought into cloth, than upon wooll carried out unwrought; untill King <note place="margin">The grounds of the preter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome.</note> 
               <hi>Iames</hi>'s time, when upon <hi>Nicholſons</hi> project, there was a further addition of charge, but ſtill upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the Statute, which is that we call the preter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted cuſtome.</p>
            <p>In Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, one or two little impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions crept in, the generall proſperitie of her raigne <note place="margin">Bates Caſe.</note> overſhadowing ſmall errours and innovations: one of theſe was upon Currants; by occaſion of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants complaints that the <hi>Venetians</hi> had laid a charg upon the Engliſh cloth, that ſo we might bee even with them, and force them the ſooner to take it off: this being demanded by King <hi>Iames,</hi> was denyed by one <hi>Bates</hi> a Merchant, and upon a ſuite in the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, was adjudged for the King. <note place="margin">The judgment therein for the King.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The manner of which judgement was thus: There
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111783:10"/>
were then but three Iudges, in that Court, all diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring from one another in the grounds of their ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. The firſt was of opinion, the King might im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon ſuch commodities as were forraign, and <note place="margin">Reſulting from different opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Iudges.</note> ſuperfluous, as Currants were, but not upon ſuch as were native, and to bee tranſported, or neceſſarie, and to bee imported for the uſe of the kingdome. The ſecond Iudge was of opinion, he might impoſe upon all forraign Merchandiſe, whether ſuperfluous or no, but not upon native. The third, that for as much as the King had the cuſtodie of the Ports, and the guard of the Seas, and that hee might open and ſhut up the parts as he pleaſed, hee had a prerogative to impoſe upon all Merchandiſe, both exported and imported.</p>
            <p>This ſingle, diſtracted and divided judgement, is <note place="margin">The only foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the power of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing,</note> the foundation of all the impoſitions now in practice: for after this, King <hi>Iames</hi> laid new charges upon all commodities outward and inward, not limited to a certaine time, and occaſion, but reſerved to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, his heires and ſucceſſors for ever: The firſt, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions in fee ſimple, that were ever heard of in this <note place="margin">followed with complaints, and preſerved by breaches of Parliaments.</note> Kingdome. This judgement, and the right of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing thereupon aſſumed was queſtioned in <hi>ſeptimo &amp; duodecimo</hi> of that King, and was the cauſe of the breach of both thoſe Parliaments. In 18. and 21. <hi>Iacobi,</hi> it was declined by this Houſe, that they might preſerve the favour of the King, for the diſpatch of ſome other great buſineſſes, upon which they were more eſpecially attentive.</p>
            <p>In 1. of his Majeſtie, It neceſſarily came to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, <note place="margin">The redreſſe deſired with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diminuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the K. profit.</note> upon the propoſition on the Kings part, for renewing the bill of Tonnage and Poundage, but ſo moderate was that Parliament, that they thought rather to confirme the impoſitions already ſet by a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111783:10"/>
Law to be made, than to aboliſh them by a judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Parliament, but that and divers inſuing Parliaments have beene unhappilie broken, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that endeavour could bee accompliſhed, only at the laſt meeting, a Remonſtrance was made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the libertie of the Subject, in this point, and it hath alwayes beene expreſt to bee the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Houſe, and ſo it was (as hee ſaid) his owne meaning in the propoſition now made, to ſettle and reſtore the right according to law, and not to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh the kings profit, but to eſtabliſh it by a free grant in Parliament.</p>
            <p>Since the breach of the laſt Parliament his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie hath by a new book of Rates very much increaſed <note place="margin">New burdens ſince the laſt Parliaments.</note> the burden upon Merchandize, and now Tonnage &amp; Poundage, old and new impoſitions are all taken by <note place="margin">Divers miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes from theſe grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> Prerogative, without any grant in Parliament, or au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of law, as we conceive, from whence divers inconveniences and miſchiefes are produced.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The danger of the preſident, that a judgement in <note place="margin">The Kingdom bound by one private caſe.</note> one Court, and in one caſe, is made binding to all the Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Mens goods are ſeized, their legall ſuits are ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, <note place="margin">Interruption of juſtice.</note> and juſtice denyed to thoſe, that deſire to take the benefit of the Law.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The great ſumms of money received upon theſe <note place="margin">Miſimployme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the ſummes received.</note> impoſitions, intended for the guard of the Seas, clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and defended upon no ground, but of publike truſt, for protection of Merchants, and defence of the ports, are diſperſed to other uſes, and a new taxe rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for the ſame purpoſes.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Theſe burdens are ſo exceſſive, that trade is <note place="margin">The burdens exceſſive.</note> thereby very much hindered, the commodities of our own, groweth extreamly abaſed, and thoſe imported
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111783:11"/>
much inhaunſed, all which lies not upon the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant alone, but upon the generalitie of the ſubject, and by this means the ſtock of the Kingdome is much diminiſht, our exportation being leſſe profitable, and our importation more chargeable. And if the warrs and troubles in the neighbour parts had not brought almoſt the whole ſtreame of Trade into this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, we ſhould have found many more prejudiciall effects of theſe impoſitions, long before this time, <note place="margin">To the Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rican plantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons eſpecially.</note> than yet we have done; eſpecially they have beene inſupportable to the poore plantations, whither ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his Majeſties ſubjects have beene transported, in divers parts of the Continent; and Iſlands of <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica,</hi> being a deſigne tending to the honour of the Kingdome, and the inlargement of his Majeſties do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions: The adventurers in this noble worke, have for the moſt part, no other ſupport but Tobacco, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which, ſuch a heavie rate is ſet, that the King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives twice as much, as the true value of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie to the owner.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Whereas theſe great burdens have cauſed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers <note place="margin">Impoſitions upon trade in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſorie.</note> Merchants to apply themſelves to a way of traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique abroad by tranſporting goods from one Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey to another, without bringing them home in to England. It hath beene lately endeavoured to ſet an Impoſition upon this trade: ſo as the King, will have a dutie out of thoſe commodities which never come within his dominions, to the great diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſuch active and induſtrious men.</p>
            <p>The next generall head of Civill grievances, was inforcing men to compound for Knighthood, which <note place="margin">Compoſitions for Knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood.</note> though it may ſeeme paſt, becauſe it is divers yeares ſince it was uſed, yet upon the ſame grounds the King may renew it, as often as he pleaſeth, for the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:111783:11"/>
compoſition lookes backward, and the offence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing, is ſubject to a new fine, The ſtate of that buſineſſe, he layed downe thus:</p>
            <p>Heretofore when the ſervices due by tenure, were <note place="margin">The Originall ground of the charge.</note> taken in kind, it were fit there ſhould be ſome way of tryall, and approbation of thoſe, that were bound to ſuch ſervices. Therefore it was ordained, that ſuch as were to doe Knights ſervices, after they came of age, and had poſſeſſion of their lands, and ſhould bee made Knights, that is, publikely declared, to bee fit for that ſervice, divers ceremonies and ſolemnities were in uſe for this purpoſe: and if by the parties neglect this was not done, he was puniſhable by fine: there being in thoſe times an ordinary and open way to get Knighthood, for thoſe who were borne to it.</p>
            <p>Although the uſe of this hath for divers ages been <note place="margin">An old grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance in the kind, but New in the manner and exceſſe, in Reſpect of The generality Greatneſſe of fines.</note> diſcontinued, yet there have paſt very few Kings, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whom there hath not been a generall Summons, requiring thoſe who had lands of ſuch value as the law preſcribes, to appeare at the Coronation, or ſome other great ſolemnitie, and to bee Knighted, and yet nothing intended but the getting of ſome ſmall fines: So as this grievance is not altogether new in the kind, though it bee new in the manner, and in the exceſſe of it, and that in divers reſpects.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Firſt, It hath beene extended beyond all inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of, and colour of law, not onely Inneholders, but likewiſe Leaſe-holders, Copy-holders, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and others, ſcarce any man free from it.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The Fines have beene Immoderate, far beyond thproportion of former times.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The proportion have beene without any exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, preſident, or rule of juſtice: for though thoſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111783:12"/>
that were ſummoned did appeare, yet diſtreſſes infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite were made out againſt them, and iſſues increaſed <note place="margin">Multiplication of diſtreſſes &amp; iſſues.</note> and multiplyed, and no way open to diſcharge thoſe iſſues, by plea or otherwiſe, but onely by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding with the commiſſioners at their owne pleaſure.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The third was, The great Inundation of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopolies, whereby heavie burthens are laid, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">Monopolies introduced by the Sope pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by papiſts.</note> upon forraigne, but alſo Native commodities. Theſe began in the Sope-Patent, the principall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakers in this, were divers popiſh Recuſants, men of eſtate and qualitie, ſuch as in likelyhood did not only aime at their private gaine, but that by this open breach of Law, the King and his people might bee more fully divided, and the wayes of Parliament men more throughly obſtructed. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the infinite inconveniences and miſchiefes <note place="margin">Full of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe.</note> which this did produce, theſe few may bee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The impairing the goodneſſe, and inhauncing the price of moſt of the Commodities and Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures <note place="margin">1 The price of commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties increaſt and goodnes abated.</note> of the Realme, yea of thoſe, who are of moſt neceſſarie and common uſe, as Salt, Sope, Beere, Coles, and infinite others.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That under colour of Licences, Trades, and Manufactures are reſtrained to a few hands, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <note place="margin">Reſtraint of trade.</note> of the Subjects deprived of their ordinary way of livelyhood.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That upon ſuch illegall grantss, a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:111783:12"/>
of perſons had beene unjuſtly vexed by <note place="margin">Illegall impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonments and vexations.</note> Purſevants, Impriſonments, attendance upon the Councell Table, ſeiſure of goods, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other wayes.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The fourth, that great and unparalleld <note place="margin">Shipmoney.</note> grievance of the Shipmoney, which though it may ſeeme to have more warrant of Law than the reſt, becauſe there hath a judgement paſt for it, yet in truth it is thereby aggravated, if it bee <note place="margin">Aggravated, not ſupported by the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> conſidered, that that judgement is founded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the naked opinion of ſome Iudges, without any written law, without any cuſtome, or au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of Law bookes, yea without any one <note place="margin">Which is not grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any law, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent or autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of law bookes.</note> preſident for it. Many expreſſe lawes, many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations in Parliaments, and the conſtant judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and practice of all times being againſt it, yea in the nature of it, it will be found to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportionable to the caſe of neceſſitie which is pretended to be the ground of it.</p>
            <p>Neceſſitie excludes all formalities and ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, <note place="margin">The courſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper for a caſe of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</note> it is no time then to make levies and tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, to build and prepare Ships, every mans per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, every mans Ships are to be imployed for the reſiſting of an invading enemie: the right on the ſubjects part was ſo cleare, and the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces againſt it ſo weake, that hee thought no man would venture his reputation or conſcience in the defence of that judgement, being ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the grounds of the Law, to the practice of former times, and ſo inconſiſtent in it ſelfe.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:111783:13"/>
amongſt many inconveniences and obliquities of <note place="margin">Abounding in varietie of Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes.</note> this grievance he noted theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That it extendeth to all perſons, and to all <note place="margin">The Generall extent and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medileſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</note> times, it ſubjected our goods to diſtreſſe, and our perſons to impriſonment, and the cauſes of it being ſecret and inviſible, referred to his Majeſties breſt alone, the ſubject was left with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out poſſibilitie of exception, and reliefe.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That there was no rules or limits for the <note place="margin">Arbitrary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion.</note> proportion, ſo that no man knew what eſtate he had, or how to order his courſe or expences.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That it was taken out of the Subjects purſe, <note place="margin">Impoſed by writ diſpoſed by inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> by a writt, and brought into the Kings Coffers by inſtructions from the Lords of his Moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable privie Councell. In the legall defence of it, the Writ only did appeare, of the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, there was no notice taken, which yet in the reall execution of it, were moſt predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. It carryes the face of ſervice in the Writ, and of Revenue in the inſtructions, if this way had not beene found to turne the Ship, into mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, it would eaſily have appeared how incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible this ſervice is with the office of a She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe, in the inland Counties, and how incongru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <note place="margin">Improper for the Sheriffes.</note> and inconvenient for the inhabitants. The law in a body politike is like nature, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes prepareth and diſpoſeth proper and fit inſtruments and Organes, for every naturall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration. <note place="margin">Vnprovided for by law.</note>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:111783:13"/>
if the Law had intended any ſuch charge as this, there ſhould have beene certaine rules, ſuitable meanes and courſes, for the levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and managing of it.</p>
            <p n="5">5 The fift was the Inlargement of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts <note place="margin">Inlargement of Forreſts.</note> beyond the bounds and perambulations ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed and eſtabliſhed by act of Parliament, twenty ſeven, and twenty eight <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>first,</hi> and that this is done upon the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons <note place="margin">Againſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Statutes.</note> and exceptions which had beene on the Kings part propounded, and by the Commons anſwered in Parliament, not long after that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhment. It is not unknowne to many in this Houſe, that thoſe perambulations were the fruit and effect of that famous Charter, which is called <hi>Charta de forreſta,</hi> whereby many tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Charta de forre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta</hi> made uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.</note> troubles, and diſcontents had beene ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, and compoſed betweene the King and his ſubjects, and it is full of danger, that by reviving thoſe old Queſtions wee may fall into the like diſtempers.</p>
            <p>He ſaid, that hereby no blame could fall upon <note place="margin">Iuſtice in Eyer cleared.</note> that great Lord, who is now Iuſtice in Eyre, and in whoſe name theſe things were acted, it could not be expected that he ſhould take notice of the lawes and cuſtomes of the realme, therefore he <note place="margin">The Anſwer lies upon the Iudges.</note> was carefull to procure the aſſiſtance and directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Iudges, and if any thing were done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt law, it was for them to anſwer, and not for him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:111783:14"/>
The particular irregularities and obliquities of <note place="margin">Particular ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquities.</note> this buſineſſe were theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The ſurreptitious procuring a verdict for the <note place="margin">Surreptitious proceedings.</note> King, without giving notice to the Countrey, whereby they might be prepared to give in evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for their owne intereſt and indemnitie; as was done in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Whereas the Iudges in the Iuſtice ſeat in <note place="margin">A judgement pretended.</note> 
               <hi>Eſſex</hi> were conſulted with, about the entry of the former verdict, and delivered their opinion touching that alone, without medling with the point of right, this opinion was after inforced in other Counties, as if it had beene a judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the matter, and the Councell for the Countie diſcountenanced in ſpeaking, becauſe it was ſaid to be already adjudged.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The inheritance of divers of the Subjects <note place="margin">The Subject diſturbed.</note> have beene hereupon diſturbed, after the quiet poſſeſſion of three or foure hundred yeares, and a way open for the diſturbance of many others.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Great ſummes of money have been drawn <note place="margin">Inforced to compound for great fines.</note> from ſuch as have lands within theſe pretended bounds, and thoſe who have forborne to make compoſition, have beene threatned with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of the forreſt lawes.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:111783:14"/>
5 The fifth, was the ſelling of Nuſances, or <note place="margin">Selling of Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſances.</note> at leaſt, ſome ſuch things as are ſuppoſed to bee Nuſances.</p>
            <p>The King as Father of the Common wealth <note place="margin">The legall try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of Nuſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces omitted.</note> is to take care of the publike Commodities, and advantages of his ſubjects, as Rivers, Highways, Common Sewers, and ſuch like, and is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move whatſoever is prejudiciall to them, and for the tryall of thoſe, there are legall and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie writs, of <hi>Ad quod damnum:</hi> but of late <note place="margin">A new extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiciall way practiſed.</note> a new and extrajudiciall way hath beene taken, of declaring matters to be Nuſances, and divers have thereupon beene queſtioned, and if they would not compound they have beene fined; If they doe compound, that which was firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted <note place="margin">Compoſitions inforced, and</note> as a common Nuſance, is taken into the Kings protection, and allowed to ſtand, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving yeelded the King Money, no further care is taken, whether it bee good or bad for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <note place="margin">A publike truſt broken or abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note> wealth. By this a very great and publike truſt is either broken or abuſed: if the matter compounded for be truly a Nuſance, then it is broken to the hurt of the people: if it bee not a Nuſance, then is it abuſed to the hurt of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: <note place="margin">The particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</note> the particulars mentioned, were:</p>
            <p>1 The Commiſſion for buildings in and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <note place="margin">Commiſſion for building.</note> this Towne, which heretofore hath beene preſented by this Houſe as a grievance in K. <hi>Iames</hi> his time, but now of late the execution hath beene much more frequent and prejudiciall than it was before.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:111783:15"/>
Secondly, Commiſſion for Depopulations, which began ſome few yeares ſince, and is ſtill <note place="margin">Depopulations</note> in hot proſecution.</p>
            <p>By both theſe, the ſubject is reſtrained from <note place="margin">The ſeverall miſchiefes of both.</note> diſpoſing of his owne, ſome have beene com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to demoliſh their houſes, others have beene forbidden to build, other after great trouble and vexation, have beene forced to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme their peace with large ſummes, and they ſtill remaine by law, as lyable to a new queſtion as before, for it is agreed by all, that the King cannot licence a common Nuſance: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in deed theſe are not ſuch, yet it is a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of very ill conſequence, that under that name they ſhould be compounded for, and may in ill times bee made a preſident for the Kings of this Realme to claime a power of licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing ſuch things as are Nuſances indeed.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh, The Militarie charges laid upon <note place="margin">Militarie char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</note> the ſeverall Counties of the Kingdome, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by warrant under his Majeſties ſignature, ſometime by Letters from the Councell Table, and ſometimes (ſuch hath been the boldneſſe and preſumption of ſome men) by the order of the Lord Leivtenants, or Deputie Lievtenant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</p>
            <p>This is a growing evill ſtill multiplying and <note place="margin">A growing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill.</note> increaſing from a few particulars to many, from ſmall ſummes to great: it began firſt to be pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:111783:15"/>
as a loane, for ſupply of coat and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct <note place="margin">Coat and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct money how practiſed by Q. Eliz.</note> money, and for this it hath ſome counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, from the uſe in Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, when the Lords of the Councell did often deſire the deputie Lievtenants to procure ſo much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to be laid out in the Countrey as the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice did require, with a promiſe to pay it againe in <hi>London;</hi> for which purpoſe there was a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant warrant in the Exchequer. This (he ſaid) was the practice in her time, and in a great part of King <hi>Iames</hi>'s, and the payments ſo certaine, as it was little otherwiſe, than taking up money upon bils of Exchange; at this day they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low theſe preſidents, in the manner of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand (for it is with a promiſe of a repayment) but not in the certaintie and readineſſe of ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
            <p>The firſt particular brought into a tax (as <note place="margin">Muſter maſters wages.</note> he thought) was the Muſter Maſters wages, at which many repined, but being for ſmall ſumms it began to bee generally digeſted: yet in the laſt Parliament, this Houſe was ſenſible of it, and to avoid the danger of the preſident that the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects ſhould be forced to make any payments without conſent in Parliament, they thought upon a Bill that may bee a rule to the Lievte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants what to demand, and to the people what to pay. But the hopes of this Bill were daſht in the diſſolution of that Parliament. Now of late divers other particulars are growing into pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:111783:16"/>
which make the grievance much more heavie: thoſe mentioned were theſe,</p>
            <p n="1">1 Preſſing men againſt their will, and forcing <note place="margin">Preſſing.</note> them which are rich or unwilling to ſerve to find others in their place.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The proviſion of publike Magazines for powder, and other Munition, Spades and <note place="margin">Publike Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zins.</note> Pickaxes.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The Salarie of Divers officers beſides the Muſter-Maſter. <note place="margin">Salary of offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 The buying of Carthorſes and Carts, and hiring of Carts for Cariages. <note place="margin">Cart-horſes and Carts.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The eighth, The extrajudiciall declarations of Iudges, whereby the ſubjects have beene <note place="margin">Extrajudiciall declarations of Iudges.</note> bound in matters of great importance without heareing of Councell or Argument on their part, and are left without legall remedie, by writ of errour or otherwiſe: he remembred the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion uſed by another member of the houſe of a teeming Parliament: this (he ſaid) was a tee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming grievance: from hence have iſſued moſt of the great grievances now in being, The Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>money, <note place="margin">A teeming grievance.</note> the pretended Nuſances already men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, and ſome others which have not yet been toucht upon: Eſpecially that concerning the proceedings of Eccleſiaſticall Courts.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:111783:16"/>
The ninth, That the authoritie and wiſedome <note place="margin">Monopolies countenanced by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell Table.</note> of the Councell Table, have beene applyed to the contriving and managing of ſeverall Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polies, and other great grievances (he ſaid) The inſtitution of the Councell Table, was much for the advantage and ſecuritie of the ſubject, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void ſurreptions and precipitate Courts in the <note place="margin">The ancient oath of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours.</note> great affaires of the Kingdome: That by law an oath is to be taken by all thoſe of the Kings Counſell, in which amongſt other things it is expreſt, that they ſhould for no cauſe forbeare to doe right, to all the Kings people, and if ſuch an oath be not now taken, he wiſht it might be brought into uſe againe.</p>
            <p>It was the honour of that Table, to bee as it <note place="margin">Their truſt &amp; dignity.</note> were incorporated with the King, his royall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and greatneſſe did ſhine moſt conſpicuouſly in their actions, and in their Councels: Wee have heard of Projectors and Reſurees hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and what opinion and reliſh they have found in this Houſe is not unknown. But that any ſuch thing ſhould be acted by the Councell Table, which might give ſtrength and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance to Monopolies, as it hath not beene uſed till now of late, ſo it cannot be apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded without the juſt griefe of the honeſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and incouragement of thoſe who are ill affected.</p>
            <p>He remembred that in <hi>Tertio</hi> of King.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:111783:17"/>
a Noble Gentleman, then a very worthy mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Commons Houſe, now a great Lord <note place="margin">Much dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note> and eminent Councellour of State, did in this place declare this opinion concerning that clauſe uſed to bee inſerted in Pattents of Monopolie, whereby Iuſtices of peace are commanded to aſſiſt the Pattentees, this hee urged as a great diſhonour to thoſe Gentlemen, which are in commiſſion to bee ſo meanely imployed, with much more reaſon, may wee in jealouſie of the <note place="margin">By being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of ſuch ill report.</note> honour of the Councell Table, humbly deſire that their precious time, their great abilities de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, to the publike care and ſervice of the Kingdome, may not receive ſuch a ſtaine, ſuch a diminution, as to be imployed in matters of ſo ill report, in the eſtimation of the law: of ſo ill effect, in the apprehenſion of the people.</p>
            <p>The tenth, The high Court of Starchamber, <note place="margin">Star-chamber a great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell.</note> which ſome thinke ſucceed that, which in the Parliament Rolles is called, <hi>Magnum Concilium,</hi> and to which, Parliaments were wont ſo often to referre thoſe important matters, which they had no time to determine. This Court, which in the late reſtauration or erection of it, in <hi>Henry</hi> 
               <note place="margin">A court ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted againſt oppreſſion.</note> the ſeventh's time, was eſpecially deſigned to reſtraine the oppreſſion of great men, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the obſtructions and impediments of the law, This which is both a Court of Councell and a Court of Iuſtice, hath beene made an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of erecting and defending Monopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:111783:17"/>
and other grievances; to ſet a face of right <note place="margin">Applyed the eſtabliſhing of Monopolies.</note> upon thoſe things, which are unlawfull in their owne nature: a face of publike good, upon ſuch as are pernicious in their uſe and execution. The Soape-patent, and divers other evidences thereof may be given, ſo well knowne, as not to require a particular relation: And as if this were not enough, this Court hath lately inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medled with the Ship money, divers Sheriffes have beene queſtioned, for not levying and collecting ſuch ſummes, as their Counties have <note place="margin">To the reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>money.</note> beene charged with, and if this beginning bee not prevented, the Starre-chamber will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Court of Revenue, and it ſhall bee made crime not to collect or pay ſuch taxes, as the State ſhall require.</p>
            <p>The eleventh, Hee ſaid, hee was gone very <note place="margin">The Kings e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations.</note> high, yet hee muſt goe a little higher: that great and moſt eminent power of the King of making Edicts and Proclamations, which are ſaid to bee <hi>Leges Temporis,</hi> with which our Princes have uſed to encounter with ſudden and unexpected danger, as would not indure ſo much delay, as aſſembling the great Councell of the Kingdome, This which is one of the moſt glorious beames of Majeſtie, moſt ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous in commanding reverence, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, <note place="margin">For the ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopolies.</note> to our unſpeakable griefe, hath been often exerciſed for the enjoyning and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining ſundry Monopolies, and other grants,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:111783:18"/>
exceeding burdenſome, and prejudiciall to the people</p>
            <p>The twelfth. Although he was come as high <note place="margin">The word and truth of God.</note> as he could upon earth, yet the preſumption of evill men did leade him one ſtep higher, even as high as Heaven, as high as the Throne of God. It was now, he ſaid, growne common, for ambitious and corrupt men of the Clergie, to abuſe the truth of God, and the bond of conſcience, preaching downe the lawes and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties <note place="margin">Pretended for the abſolute power of Kings.</note> of the Kingdome, pretending Divine authoritie, for an abſolute power in the King, to doe what hee would with our perſons, and goods, this hath beene often publiſhed in Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and Printed bookes, and is now the high way to preferment.</p>
            <p>The laſt Parliament, wee had a ſentence for an offence of this kind, againſt one <hi>Manne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The offence of D. <hi>Mannaring.</hi>
               </note> then a Doctor, now a Biſhop, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whom (hee ſaid) hee would ſay no more but this, that when hee ſaw him at his Barre, in the moſt humble dejected poſture, that ever hee obſerved, hee thought hee would not ſo ſoone have leapt into a Biſhops chaire, but his ſucceſſe hath emboldened others, therefore (he ſaid) this may well bee noted as a double grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, that ſuch doctrine ſhould bee allowed, <note place="margin">Now practiſed by others.</note> that ſuch men ſhould bee preferred, yea as a roote of grievances whereby they indeavour
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111783:18"/>
to corrupt the Kings conſcience, and as much <note place="margin">To the great hurt and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of the people.</note> as in them lyes, to deprive the people of that Royall protection, to which his Majeſtie is bound by the fundamentall Lawes of the Kingdome, and his owne perſonall oath.</p>
            <p>The thirteenth: The long intermiſſion of <note place="margin">The Intermiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> Parliaments, contrary to the two ſtatutes yet in force, whereby it is appointed there ſhould bee Parliaments once a yeare, at the leaſt, and moſt contrary to the publike good of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, for this being well remedied would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce remedies for all the reſt.</p>
            <p>Having put through the ſeverall heads of <note place="margin">The ſubjects grievances hurtfull to the King.</note> grievances, hee came to the ſecond maine branch, propounded in the beginning. That the diſorders from whence theſe grievances iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, were as hurtfull to the King, as to the people, of which hee gave divers reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The interruption of the ſweet communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">Bb interrupt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> their commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</note> which ought to bee betwixt the King and his people, in matters of grace and ſupply. They have need of him by his generall pardon, to be ſecured from projectors, and informers, to bee freed from obſolete lawes, from the ſubtle devices of ſuch as ſeeke to reſtraine the Prerogative to their owne private advantage, and the publike hurt; and he hath need of them for councell and ſuport, in great and extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:111783:19"/>
occaſions. This mutuall intercourſe would ſo weane the affections and intereſts of his ſubjects, into his actions and deſignes, that their wealth and their perſons would bee his, his owne eſtate would bee managed to moſt advantage, and publike, undertakings would bee proſecuted at the charge and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture of the ſubject: The victorious at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts in Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time upon <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, Spaine,</hi> and the <hi>Indies,</hi> were for the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part, made upon the ſubjects purſes, and not upon the Queenes, though the honour and profit of the ſucceſſe, did moſt accrew to her.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Thoſe often breaches and diſcontentments <note place="margin">By domeſticall breaches and diſcontents.</note> betwixt the King and the people, are very apt to diminiſh his reputation abroad, and diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage his treaties and alliances.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The apprehenſion of the favour and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement <note place="margin">By weakning his partie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad.</note> given to Poperie, hath much weakned his Majeſties partie beyond the Sea, and impared that advantage which Queene <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth</hi> and his Royall Father have hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore made, of being heads of the Proteſtant union.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The innovations in Religion and rigour of <note place="margin">By forcing his ſubjects to leave the Kingdome.</note> Eccleſiaſticall Courts, have forced a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his Majeſties ſubjects to forſake the land,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:111783:19"/>
whereby not onely their perſons, and their poſteritie, but their wealth, and their indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrey are loſt to this Kingdome, much to the demoliſhing of his Majeſties Cuſtomes and Subſidies. Amongſt other Inconveniences, this was eſpecially to be obſerved, that divers Clothiers driven out of the Countrey, had ſet up the manufacture of Cloth beyond the Seas, whereby this State is like to ſuffer much by abatement of the price of Woolls, and by want of imployment for the poore, both which likewiſe tend to his Majeſties particular loſſe.</p>
            <p n="5">5 It puts the King upon unproper wayes <note place="margin">By unproper wayes of ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply.</note> of ſupply, which being not warranted by law, are much more burdenſome to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, than advantagious to his Majeſtie. In <hi>France</hi> not long ſince, upon a ſurvey of the Kings Revenue, it was found that two parts in three, never came to the Kings purſe, but were diverted to the profit of the officers or miniſters of the Crowne, and it was thought a very good ſervice and reformation, to reduce two parts to the King, leaving ſtill a third part to the Inſtruments as were imployed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout getting it in. It may well bee doubted, that the King may have the like or worſe ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe in England: which appeares already in ſome particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:111783:20"/>
The King hath reſerved upon this Monopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Wines, Thirty thouſand Pound Rent a yeere, the Vintner payes Fourty Shillings a Tun, which comes to Ninty thouſand pounds: the price upon the Subject by retaile, is increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Two pence a Quart, which comes to Eight pound a Tun, and for Fourty five thouſand Tun brought in yeerly, amounts to Three hundred ſixty thouſand pounds, which is Three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and Thirty thouſand pounds loſſe to the Kingdome, above the Kings Rent; other Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopolies, as that of Soape, have beene very chargable to the Kingdome, and brought very little Treaſure into his Majeſties Coffers.</p>
            <p>The law provides for that revenue of the Crowne; which is Naturall and proper, that it may be ſafely collected, and brought to Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, but this illegall Revenue, being without any ſuch proviſion, is left to hazard, and much uncertainty, either not to be reteined, or not duly accounted of.</p>
            <p n="6">6 It is apt to weaken the Induſtrie and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of the Subject, if they be left uncertaine: <note place="margin">By weakening the induſtry and courage of the ſubject.</note> whether they ſhall reape the benefit of their owne paines, and hazard thoſe who are brought into the Condition of ſlaves, will eaſily grow to a ſlaviſh diſpoſition, who having nothing to looſe, doe commonly ſhew more boldneſſe in diſturbing, than in defending a Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:111783:20"/>
7 Theſe irregular Courſes doe give oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie to ill Inſtruments, to inſinuate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <note place="margin">By introducing ill Inſtruments into the Kings ſervice.</note> into the Kings ſervice, for we cannot but obſerve, that if a man be officious in furthering their inordinate burdens of Ship money, Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polies, and the like<hi>:</hi> it varniſheth over all other faults, and makes him fit both for Imployment and Preferment: So that out of their offices, they are furniſht for vaſt expences, purchaſes, Buildings; and the King loſeth often more in deſperate debts at their deaths, than he got by them all their lives, whether this were not late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly verified in a Weſterne man, much imployed while he lived: he leaves to the Knowledge of thoſe who were acquainted with his Courſe, and he doubted not but others might be found in the like caſe.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that are Affected to Popery, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſſe, and to ſuperſtitious innovations, in matters of Religion. All Kinde of Spies and intelligencers have meanes to be countenanced and truſted if they will be but zealous in theſe kinde of ſervices, which how much it detracts from his Majeſtie, in honour, in profit and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie of publike affaires, lyes open to every mans apprehenſion: and from theſe reaſons or ſome of them, he thought it proceeded that through the whole courſe of the Engliſh ſtory it might be obſerved, that thoſe Kings who had beene moſt reſpectfull of the lawes, had
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:111783:21"/>
beene moſt eminent in Greatneſſe, in Glory and ſucceſſe, both at home and abroad; and that others, who thought to ſubſiſt by the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of them, did often fall into a ſtate of weakeneſſe, povertie, and Infortunitie.</p>
            <p n="8">8 The differences and diſcontents betwixt <note place="margin">By diverting the Kings thoughts from divers great and hopefull enterpriſes.</note> his Majeſtie, and the people at home, have in all likelyhood diverted his Royall thoughts and Councells from thoſe great opportunities which he might have, not only to weaken the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> to reſtore the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> but to gaine to himſelf a higher pitch of power and greatneſſe, than any of his Anceſtors.</p>
            <p>It is not unknowne how weake, how diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, how diſcontented the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Colonies are in the <hi>Weſt Indies.</hi> There are now in thoſe parts in New <hi>England, Virginia,</hi> and the <hi>Caribe-Iſlands,</hi> and in the <hi>Barmudos,</hi> at leaſt Sixty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand able perſons of this Nation, many of them well armed, and their bodies ſeaſoned to that Climate, which with a very ſmall charge might be ſet downe in ſome advantagious parts of theſe pleaſant, rich and fruitfull Countreys, and eaſily make his Majeſtie Maſter of all that treaſure, which not onely foments the Warre, but is the great ſupport of Popery in all parts of Chriſtendome. <note place="margin">By producing many charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9 Laſtly, Thoſe courſes are apt to produce
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:111783:21"/>
ſuch diſtempers in the ſtate, as may not be ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led without great charge and loſſe, by which means more may be conſumed in a few months than ſhall be gotten by ſuch wayes in many yeeres.</p>
            <p>Having paſt through the two firſt generall <note place="margin">The wayes of remedyinge their grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> Branches, he was now come to the third, wherein he was to ſet downe the wayes of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and removing thoſe grievances; which conſiſted of two maine Branches, firſt in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring the law where it was doubtfull. The ſecond in better proviſion for the execution of law, where it is cleere: But (hee ſaid) becauſe he had already ſpent much time, and began to finde ſome confuſion in his Memory, he would referre the particulars to another opportunity, and for the preſent onely move that, which was generall to all, and would give waight and Advantage to all the particular wayes of Redreſſe; that is, that wee ſhould ſpeedily deſire a Conference with the Lords, and acquaint them with the Miſerable Condition wherein wee finde the Church and State, and as we have already reſolved to joyn in a religious ſeeking of God, in a day of faſt and humiliation, ſo to intreat them to concurre with us, in a Parliamentary courſe, of petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the King as there ſhould bee occaſion, and in ſearching out the cauſes and remedies of theſe many inſupportable grievances under which
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:111783:22"/>
we lye, that ſo by the united wiſedome and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of both Houſes, ſuch courſes may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, as (through Gods bleſſing) may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the honour and Greatneſſe of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and reſtore and eſtabliſh the peace and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>This (he ſaid) Wee might undertake with comfort and hope of ſucceſſe<hi>:</hi> for though there be a darkneſſe upon the land, a thick and palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble darkneſſe, like that of <hi>Egypt;</hi> yet as in that, the Sunne had not loſt his light, nor the <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> their ſight, the interruption was onely in the <hi>Medium,</hi> ſo with us there is ſtil (God be thanked) light in the Sun, Wiſedome and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in his Majeſtie to diſpell this darkneſſe, and in us there remaines a viſual faculty, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee are inabled to apprehend, and moved to deſire light, and when we ſhall be bleſſed in the enjoying of it, we ſhall thereby be incited to returne his Majeſtie ſuch thanks, as may make it ſhine more cleerly in the world, to his owne glory, and in the hearts of his people, to their joy and contentment.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
